Bauchwitz, Kurt (Roy C. Bates); Papers ger011
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Roy C. Bates (Kurt Bauchwitz) Papers
1890-2006
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Bauchwitz, Kurt, 1890-1974
ger011
19 cubic ft. 1 Digital Files
This collection primarily documents the literary and legal careers of Roy C. Bates (Kurt Bauchwitz). The materials document his early years in Germany (1890-1938), the years of flight from Hitler's Germany via Japan to the United States (1938-1941), and his U.S. years (1941-1974).
Biographical Sketch
Kurt Bauchwitz was born in Halle (Saale), Germany on July 12, 1890 to Edmund and Ida (Sachs) Bauchwitz. Kurt exhibited a talent for writing at an early age and published his first serious writing piece at the age of fourteen. During his childhood, he also studied piano and gave his first concert at sixteen, however decided against pursuing a career in music as too time-consuming. After graduating from gymnasium in 1908, Bauchwitz attended the universities of Grenoble, Munich, Berlin and Halle, where he studied law, completing his studies in 1912. During his university years, he continued to write poems and aphorisms and published pieces in Der Jugend and Nord und Süd.
At the conclusion of his studies in 1912, Bauchwitz was appointed Referendar and served as a junior judge and barrister until 1921. During this time period, Bauchwitz also served in the German army, having volunteered for service in October of 1913. He was called to active duty in 1914, served on the Western Front until the end of the war, and received both the Iron Cross and Medal of Honor for bravery. Also during this time period, he continued to write poetry, composing many of the poems later published in his first and only published volume of poetry, Der Lebendige (1920), while serving in the German army. Bauchwitz married Else Schwabach on February 22, 1917, who gave birth to their first son, Kurt Helmut, on April 22, 1919, and a second son, Till, on May 9, 1922. Bauchwitz was widowed in 1931 by the death of his wife Else on March 15.
From 1921 to 1938 Bauchwitz practiced law in Berlin, receiving his degrees of Pol.Sc.D. and LL.D. from the University of Halle in 1924.. He specialized in international commercial law, family and social law. In 1926 he received the appointment of Notar (notary), by the Minister of Justice. This appointment was revoked by Nazi legislation effective November 1935 which deprived all "non-Aryan" Notare of their profession. In November 1938, his right to practice law was terminated for the same reason. As a result, Bauchwitz was forced to close his Berlin law firmoffice. Two years later, his right to practice law is terminated, and in November of 1938, Bauchwitz is forced to close his Berlin law office.
His termination in 1938, marked the beginning of a series of radical changes for Bauchwitz. Later that year, on December 16, Bauchwitz married his secretary Hilde Michaelis. Just prior to his departure from Hitler's Germany in March 1939, Bauchwitz is baptized as a Catholic. On April 3, 1939, Bauchwitz leaves Nazi Germany. After several months, Bauchwitz, his new wife and two sons arrive in Japan, where they remain for nearly eighteen months before their eventual departure for the United States on November 20, 1940. The period, which began with Bauchwitz' departure from Germany and ended with his eventual arrival in the U.S. in December of 1941, was one of his most fertile creative periods. During this time, he collected many of his earlier poems and epigrammatic verse to form the collection he called the "Abzieh-Bilderbuch". In addition, he wrote over 200 poems, later entitled his "Tokyo poems", which would also be the last significant collection of poetry in German he would write.
Following his arrival in New York City, Kurt Bauchwitz, German writer and lawyer, would become Roy C. Bates, on his way to becoming a naturalized American citizen and writer. In 1941, Bates' divorced and from 1942-1943 Bates pursued a course of study at the Columbia University School of Library Science, receiving a B.S. degree in October 1943. Bates' diligent efforts at perfecting his English language skills result in securing him an editorial position on the Funk & Wagnalls New Standard Encyclopeida staff from 1944 to 1947. Bauchwitz also becomes an American citizen on May 6, 1946, legally changing his name from Kurt Bauchwitz to Roy Curt Bates at this time, and less than two years later, marries Barbara Bent, on March 16, 1948.
Although Bates continued to write during the late 1940s and early 1950s, composing poems, epigrams, short prose, and even song texts in English, only one of his efforts in English saw publication despite his continued attempts to find publication outlets for his writings.
The 1950s saw the resumption of Bates' legal career with his return to the study of law, first at St. John's University (1953-1954) and later at New York University (1954-1956), where he received his LL.B. degree in February 1956. On June 19, less than one month before his 67th birthday, Roy C. Bates became the oldest person at that time to be admitted to the Bar and practice in New York State. Several years later in 1962, after relocating to Milton, Massachusetts, Bates was also admitted to the Massachusetts State Bar.
Bates continued to write during the 1950s and 1960s, however, his writing took the form of semi-autobiographical observations, which he recorded on a regular, often a daily, basis. Three series of these collections of observations, the first series entitled "Pebbles" and the later two entitled "Quotation Marks", make up the bulk of his writing activity during this time. Bates also became interested in the legal aspects of psychedelic drugs during the 1960s, which resulted in his participation in the M.I.T.-based Neurobiological and Psychedelic Study Group, as well as publication of an article on "Psychedelics and the Law" in 1964.
Although Roy Curt Bates (Kurt Bauchwitz) was a lawyer by profession both in Germany and later in the United States specializing in international law, his enthusiasm for writing which began in early childhood, survived the change from a German-speaking to an American writer, and is evidenced by the large body of written work he left behind. Bates died in Milton, Massachusetts on July 18, 1974 at the age of 84.
Chronology of Events:
1890 July 12, born in Halle (Saale), Germany
1906-1908 Attends gymnasium in Halle (Saale)
1908 March, graduates from Stadtgymnasium, Halle
1908-1912 University study at the Universities of Grenoble (France) and Berlin, Munich and Halle (Germany)
1912 Appointed Referendar
1912-1921 Serves as junior judge and barrister
1913 Oct., volunteers for the army
1914-1918 Serves in the German Army on the Western front, receives Iron Cross and medal for bravery.
1917 Feb. 22, marries Else Schwabach.
1919 Apr. 22, birth of son, Helmut Kurt.
1920 Publication of Der Lebendige
1921 Jan., appointed Assessor (judge lateral)
1921-1938 Practices law in Berlin
1922 May 9, birth of son, Tyll Kurt.
1924 June 20, receives degrees of Pol.Sc.D. and LL.D. from Halle.
1926 Receives appointment of Notar by the Minister of Justice
1929 Tourist visit to Soviet Russia.
1931 Mar. 15, death of first wife, Else Schwabach.
1936 Jan. 31, appointment as Notar is terminated by Hitler regime
1938 Right to practice law terminated by Hitler regime; closes Berlin law office in Nov.; Dec. 16, marries Hilde Michaelis.
1939 Mar. 19, is baptized as a Catholic in Berlin; Apr. 3, leaves Hamburg, Germany by ship; May 29, arrives in Kobe, Japan.
1939-1940 Spends a year and a half in Tokyo, en route to U.S.
1940 Nov. 20, leaves Japan; travels to U.S. via Hawaii and Canada; Dec. 9, arrives in San Francisco, CA; Dec. 26, arrives in New York City.
1941 Settles in New York City; takes out "first papers" for American citizenship; Apr. 18, divorces Carole Hildegard Bates (formerly Hilde Michaelis).
1942-1943 Attends Columbia University, School of Library Science
1943 Oct. 27, receives B.S. degree in Library Science from Columbia Univ.
1944-1947 Serves as editor of the Funk & Wagnalls New Standard Encyclopedia
1946 May 6, becomes U.S. citizen, legally changing his name to Roy Curt Bates
1948 Mar. 16, marries Barbara Bent, an American
1953-1956 Studies law at St. John's University and New York University
1956 Fe., receives LL.B. degree from New York University
1957 June 19, admitted to the New York State Bar
1959 Returns to Europe for the first time since 1939.
1960 Moves to Milton, Massachusetts
1961 Attends Buddhist Summer School in Cambridge, England.
1962 May 9, admitted to the Massachusetts State Bar
1974 July 18, dies in Milton, Massachusetts
Scope and Contents
The Roy C. Bates Papers, 1890-1994, concentrate primarily on the literary career of Bates/Bauchwitz (1910-1974), with a secondary emphasis on the legal career of Bates. The materials document his early years in Germany (1890-1938), the years of flight from Hitler Germany via Japan to the United States (1938-1941), and his U.S. years (1941-1974).
The collection is divided into six series: 1) biographical materials, including documents, 1890-1974; 2) correspondence and related materials, 1914-1987; 3) manuscripts and typescripts, 1928-1974; 4) publications, 1910-1972; 5) miscellaneous materials, arranged by subject; and 6) oversize materials. The earlier materials (pre-1941) are in German, with materials after 1941 primarily in English.
The biographical materials contain many early documents, including school and university diplomas, birth and marriage certificates, German military record, and documents pertaining to Bauchwitz's dismissal from his legal position by the Hitler regime. Also included in this section are a series of curriculum vitae, as well as several biographical statements intended as introductions to volumes of poetry, and a small number of photographs.
The correspondence consists of nearly 5,000 letters, primarily 1941-1974, and has been divided into five sub-categories, arranged alphabetically within each sub-series: 1) personal, which represents the largest section and includes correspondences with family members (esp. his two sons) and life-long friends; 2) legal correspondences; 3) correspondences re: literary topics and publications; 4) correspondence re: psychedelic drugs and schizophrenia; and 5) miscellaneous correspondences.
The manuscripts and typescripts have been divided between poetry (including epigrammatic verse and aphorisms) and prose. The poetry section, dating from circa 1926, is primarily written in German, with the exception of his later epigrammatic verse collections "Ego and Echo" and "Monogrips", which are in English. The prose sub-series includes short prose pieces (the majority written in English) and his loosely autobiographical collections of daily observations, which span nearly three decades, 1950-1966, which he entitled "Pebbles" (later "Question Marks").
The publications section contains copies, either in the original or in photocopy, of nearly all of Bauchwitz'/Bates' published writings, including his first and only published volume of verse Der Lebendige (1920), as well as his many published "Letters to the Editor.".
The miscellaneous materials section has been sub-divided into the materials of Roy C. Bates and those of his wife, Barbara Bent Bates. The Roy C. Bates materials consist primarily of clippings and materials files, arranged alphabetically by subjects on legal topics, organizations and other subjects of interest to Bates. The Barbara Bates materials are divided between her own writings (and publications) and her attempts to publish her husband's writings posthumously. Oversize materials consist of diplomas (2), as well as two paintings, which were probably given to the Bates as gifts.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into six series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Mrs. Barbara Bent Bates in 1987 and 1988. A small amount of additional materials were donated in 2005 by Mrs. Harry (Judy) Zorn.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Literature; Lawyers--New York (State)--New York.; German literature--Japanese influences.; Protest poetry, German.; Exiles' writings, German.; German American poetry.; Germany--Emigration and immigration; Japan--Intellectual life; Poems; Manuscripts; Correspondence; Diaries; Digital Files; Bauchwitz, Kurt, 1890-1974.
- Biographical Materials, 1890-2006; 1; 31 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents, several selections of diary entries, photographs and curriculum vita of Bates. The documents pertaining to Roy C. Bates (Kurt Bauchwitz) date from 1890 to 1974 with later documents pertaining to Barbara Bates (third wife), which date through 1995. Included in the collection are many early documents such as birth certificates, early school documents, marriage certificates from Bates/Bauchwitz' first two marriages in Germany, as well as university and military service documents. Also in the collection are a number of documents which record Bates/Bauchwitz' legal career as well as his subsequent dismissal from his post by the Hitler regime in 1938. His period of flight from Nazi Germany is also well-documented, as well as his early years in the U.S., including his naturalization as a U.S. citizen in 1946. Also included in this section are documents pertaining to his university studies in the U.S. at Columbia, St. John's and New York Universities. Completing the biographical section of this series are a number of curriculum vita, several biographical statements prepared for planned editions of Bates' poetry, as well as a number of photographs.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Documents relating to the parents of Roy C. Bates (Kurt Bauchwitz), including marriage certificate, death certificate of father (Edmund Bauchwitz), Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 1)
  - Early documents relating to Kurt Bauchwitz and family, 1890-1918 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 2)
    Includes birth certificate, early school documents, marriage certificate of Kurt Bauchwitz and Else Schwabach, birth certificates of Helmut Bauchwitz (son), marriage certificate of Lotte Bauchwitz (sister) and Paul Sernau; record of military service of Kurt Bauchwitz.
  - University documents, 1924-1926 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 3)
  - Documents, 1933-1939 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 4)
    Including driver's licenses, identification papers, dismissal papers.
  - Marriage certificate (December 16, 1938) and subsequent divorce (April 18, 1941) documents, Roy C. Bates and Carole Hildegard Bates; also baptismal certificate of Roy C. Bates, March 19, 1939, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 5)
  - Affidavit of support from Ernst Bloch, 1939 January 13 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 6)
  - Japan documents, 1939-1940 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 7)
  - Immigration and naturalization papers, 1941-1946 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 8)
  - Columbia University records, 1941-1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 9)
    Including application materials, grades and copy of diploma.
  - Census of property in foreign countries documents, ca. 1943 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 10)
  - Law school records, bar exam, 1954-1957 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 11)
  - Admission to the bar, Court of Appeals: applications, certificates, 1957-1958 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 12)
  - Income tax records, 1945-1952 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 13)
  - Death notice, obituaries, memorial service for Roy C. Bates, 1974 July (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 14)
  - Barbara Bates, Last Will and Testament. Three versions, 1975 March 07; 1988; 1995 May 04 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 15)
    Various handwritten notes concerning bequests. ca. 20p.
  - Diary entries, dated Tokyo, 1939-1940 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 16)
    Autograph 3p. Typescript 12p.
  - Diary entries, dated New York, 1941-1941; 10p (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 17)
  - Diary entries, 1951-1971; 5p (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 18)
  - Photographs, 1.19 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 19-22)
    - Ella Schwabach, first wife of Roy C. Bates, Undated; 2 items (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 19)
    - Roy C. Bates (Kurt Bauchwitz), pre-1940; 12 items, 1 sheet of proofs (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 20)
    - Roy C. Bates, 1940s; 12 photographs, ca. 30 negatives (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 21)
    - Roy C. Bates, 1950s-1960s; 23 items (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 22)
  - Business cards (Kurt Bauchwitz), stationery (Roy C. Bates), Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 23)
  - Curriculum vita. Various versions, 1940-1974 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 24)
  - Biographical statements, 1.22 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 25-28)
    - Biographical statement, prepared in anticipation of the publication of the "Abzieh-Bilderbuch". Several versions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 25)
    - Biographical statement, prepared in anticipation of the publication of "Das Zitronenbaum". Several versions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 26)
    - Various versions, drafts of biographical statements, many authored or revised by Barbara Bates, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 27)
    - Handwritten notes (Barbara Bates) with biographical information used in preparation of statements, Undated; ca. 50p (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 28)
  - Harry Zohn. "The Transformation of a Poet", Germanic Notes, V, No. 3 (1974), p. 34-40. Offprint of article, Undated; 10p (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 29)
  - Zohn, Harry. "Wiederbegegnung mit einem verschollenen Dichter" (Introduction to Ego und Echo), Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 30)
  - Zohn, Harry. "Vorspruch zur amerikanischen Ausgabe 'Hilarious Passage' des Abzieh-Bilderbuches", Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 31)
  - Thomas Hansen. "Kurt Bauchwitz (Roy C. Bates): Exilautor sucht einen Charakter", Undated; 20p (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 32)
    Accompanied by notes, observations by Barbara Bates. Typescript 11p.
  - Articles pertaining to Bates' literary career, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 33)
  - Articles pertaining to Bates' involvement in the American Association of D.M. ccount Holders, Undated; 3 items (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 34)
  - Evelein, Johannes. "Heim-Findungen -- Lebensbuch eines Emigranten". Draft of 2006 publication of Bates/Bauchwitz' selected writings, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Materials), Folder 34a)
- Correspondence Files, 1914-1987; 2; 1 Digital Files 429 file folders
  The correspondence files contain photographs, offprints and clippings in addition to the correspondence (ca. 5,000 letters), which dates primarily from Bates' U.S. years (1941-1974), although a few earlier letters are present in the collection. Several correspondences were continued after Bates' death in 1974 by his widow, Barbara, until as late as 1987. Letters are in German, English and French and have been divided into five sub-series: personal, legal, literary, mental health and drug research, and miscellaneous.
  Arranged alphabetically within each sub-series.
  - Correspondence with Family and Friends, 1914-1987; 2.1; 89 file folders
    Includes correspondence (2558 letters), as well as related photographs (106 photos), offprints and clippings, of Roy C. Bates (and after his death in 1974 continued by Barbara Bates) with friends and family members. Most notable among the personal correspondents are: Helmut circa Bates (son), wife, Dorit, and children Kenny and Denny; Tyll Bates (son) and wife, Francy; Wilhelm (Willy) and Imma von Bodmershof (née Ehrenfels), which includes correspondence during the early 1950s documenting Bodmershof's efforts to help Bates publish his poetry; Dr. Henry and Doris Brann; Dr. Ilse Bry; Baron Umar Rolf and Mireille Abeille von Ehrenfels, the most extensive correspondence in the collection, dating from 1939-1974 between Ehrenfels and Bates, and continuing between Barbara Bates and Mireille Abeille (1974-1987), documenting their combined efforts to publish Bates' work posthumously; Eva and Hans Friede; Erika Mann (and family members, Golo, Katja, and Klaus), 1940-1962, including legal correspondence over copyright issues in the filming of Thomas Mann's Der Zauberberg; Ilse and Bernhard Reichenbach.
    - Adler, Erving H. and Hilde, 1961-1970 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 35)
      6 letters from, 4 letters to.
    - Arensberg, Max and Beryl, 1941-1974 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 36)
      19 letters from, 12 letters to; contract between Arensberg and R.C.B., dated October 1949.
    - Bates, Barbara, 1958 January-1958 February (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 37)
      1 postcard and 14 empty envelopes.
    - Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit, 1941-1943; 1953-1973; 2.1.4 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 38-44)
      206 letters from, 101 letters to; photographs.
      - Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit, 1941-1943 (Box 1 (2.1.4-Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit), Folder 38)
      - Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 1 (2.1.4-Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit), Folder 39)
      - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 1 (2.1.4-Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit), Folder 40)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 1 (2.1.4-Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit), Folder 41)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 1 (2.1.4-Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit), Folder 42)
      - Photographs, Tyll and Helmut Bates, 1920s; 16 items (Box 1 (2.1.4-Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit), Folder 43)
      - Photographs, Helmut and Dorit Bates, their two sons, Kenneth and Dennis, 1958-1970; 57 items (Box 1 (2.1.4-Bates, Helmut C. and Dorit), Folder 44)
    - Bates, Tyll and Francy, 1941-1973 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 45)
      67 letters from, 30 letters to.
    - Bates, Tyll and Francy. Photographs of daughter, Ruthie, 1957; 4 items (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 46)
    - Bauchwitz, Ida (née Sachs, mother), 1941 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 47)
      1 letter from.
    - Baumann, (Dr.) Anny, 1941-1942; 1963 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 48)
      3 letters from, 4 letters to.
    - Bent, John C., 1968 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 49)
      1 letter to.
    - Bodmershof, Wilhelm (Willy) and Imma (née Ehrenfels) von. Correspondence, 1939-1973; 2.1.10 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 50-53)
      48 letters from, 68 letters to; manuscripts; clippings.
      - Correspondence, 1939-1954 (Box 1 (2.1.10-Bodmershof, Wilhelm (Willy) and Imma (née Ehrenfel), Folder 50)
      - Correspondence, 1955-1973 (Box 1 (2.1.10-Bodmershof, Wilhelm (Willy) and Imma (née Ehrenfel), Folder 51)
      - Bodmershof, Imma und Wilhelm. "Zündholz. Deutsche Haiku" (Box 1 (2.1.10-Bodmershof, Wilhelm (Willy) and Imma (née Ehrenfel), Folder 52)
        Typescript cc. 53p.
      - Bodmershof, Wilhelm. "Studie über das Haiku" (Box 1 (2.1.10-Bodmershof, Wilhelm (Willy) and Imma (née Ehrenfel), Folder 52)
        Typescript cc. 22p.
      - Clippings, death notices, 5 items (Box 1 (2.1.10-Bodmershof, Wilhelm (Willy) and Imma (née Ehrenfel), Folder 53)
    - Brann, (Dr.) Henry Walter and Doris, 1949-1973 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 1)
      87 letters from; 48 letters to; poem text.
    - Brann, Henry, Undated; 68 items (Box 2 (2-Correspondence Files), Folder 2)
      Reprints, cl.